if you guys don't know Dave Lee you've
probably seen on the panels and
everything that he would be great
reading bedtime stories to people his
voice is just so
soothing his wisdom is beyond what I
have ever imagine would you believe that
he's only 31 years old too and he comes
across so mature and everything and I
met
Dave three years ago four years ago is
like didn't believe that he was real
because I've known him online for like
three and a half four years and finally
we were all in an Airbnb at the Olympia
this weekend and we called it like the
real world Olympia um living with Five
Guys total great idea great idea um
anyway so he it was like Dave he's like
him in person because last year we had
all intentions to bring him over for
silver back but he was on the screen
because of restrictions in America and
stuff so um but like Luke I also spent
hours on Zoom with Dave mentoring me
because like myself uh he is not a
medical doctor but he has a very
extensive background he is extremely
intelligent he knows [__] that many
Physicians ask him for his opinion on so
you guys are in for a real treat in
addition to his voice and he's also
become just a great friend and I cannot
wait for Dave to speak Dave Lee
[Applause]
yes I am all right hello everyone my
name is Dave Lee I am a health coach
from Australia today I'm going to be
giving my speech uh your brain on
testosterone the war and masculinity
part three this came about when Ally
first put this Summit together she said
you can just get up and talk about
whatever the [__] you want
so I did and then I did that again last
year for part two I don't think we
needed a part three but I just like
things in threes so this is going to be
part three it could have been called
something else but particularly what
we're going to go through today is a
little bit of stuff that will be
familiar stuff that's being discussed at
the conference so far and then a few
more things that we're going to go a
little bit down the esoteric rabbit hole
but not too deep and we're going to talk
about the relationship between biology
and consciousness which is something
that I think is very important there's a
few things I want to recap from part one
and part two so if you've seen part one
and part two this shouldn't be too
boring if you haven't seen it this will
kind of put us all on the same page for
today so Point number one testosterone
plays a key role in a man's physical and
mental health thank you Ed but it is not
a Panacea this is basically part one
summarized in one sentence so I just
saved you all an hour this is a really
important point that comes up when
you're working with guys on this this is
not covered in the mechanistic theory
this is not covered in the double blind
Placebo controlled trials this is the
stuff that you work out when you
actually work with guys in the trenches
on fixing their testosterone
testosterone will act as a foundation
for a man to get his physical and mental
health together but it does not do the
work for him and it is not a miracle
cure number two testosterone replacement
therapy is a catalyst for change in
overall health and wellness but requires
men to overhaul their habits to be in
keeping with a healthy high testosterone
male this is where expectations fall
short if you are going to have optimal
testosterone levels what you would argue
is the optimal physiological amount for
a healthy male you need to be an
optimally physically healthy male for
that to work that's just how it works so
many trt issues are due to unrealistic
expectations both in time frame and
impact of results if it took you a
decade to get your life off track it is
going to take more than 10 weeks to get
your life back on track adding in extra
ancillaries adding in a bit of extra
oxandrolone or Pyon is not going to
solve the problems that only time and
work can heal so trt will give you the
results you deserve and know more and it
takes years to fully manifest so trt is
not going to make you
a coked up entrepreneur libido through
the sky like a horny 16-year-old 24/7
that's not going to happen What is is
going to happen is you will get the
results that you deserve from your
training you will get the results that
you deserve from your recovery but no
more this is what we are getting with
testosterone optimization and the last
point which I think a lot of us know
from going outside and just walking
around is the average male's Health not
the average male in here the average
male's Health out there is on average
[__] terrible so HRT repairs the
foundation of a man's physical and
mental health when he makes positive
diet and lifestyle interventions once
his hormon hormones have been optimized
he will get get the results he deserves
in time trt supplements and biohacks I
hate that word will not fix
self-destructive diet and lifestyle
habits particularly drugs alcohol and
junk food in practice when you're Health
coaching guys on trt the majority of
issues that come down the track with trt
quote unquote not working properly is
because they're putting drugs alcohol
and junk food into their bodies
including SSRI
anti-depressants a multigenerational and
lifelong exposure to endocrine
disruptors has negatively impacted
healthy young men we know that there are
multiple factors why younger men are
having lower testosterone levels and
poorer physical and mental health than
their fathers and grandfathers and one
thing that absolutely plays a role is
the pollutions pesticides and poisons I
like things in threes so often times it
is the or origal unresolved cause of the
secondary
hypogonadism that causes the side
effects on trt so this is a really
important point if your body is shutting
down your natural testosterone
production because you're treating your
body like [__] if you don't stop
treating your body like [__] and putting
in a [__] ton of testosterone you are
going to get problems whether you like
it or not so it's like taking a Ferrari
engine and putting it into an old Suzuki
Swift you're going to rip out of the car
park absolutely and then it's going to
fall apart in 8 to 12 weeks so without
getting into too much of an egotistical
rant about myself I am a health coach
specializing in men's hormone
optimization therapy and everything
around and in between this topic so I
got into working with trt after dropping
out of neuros Psychiatry I was
interested in healing the brain not
learning how to drug people and what got
me into the troubleshooting around trt
was my interest in problem solving so a
lot of guys were coming to me there were
on X protocol from why doctor and things
just weren't working properly and my
brain needed to know why that was so my
background before I did this was
mindfulness meditation and and what got
me uh into the field of Health
originally was I Had a Brain Injury so I
had debilitating vestibular neuritis for
two years um it completely destroyed my
physical and mental health and
testosterone was what allowed me to
actually go through the rehabilitation
that I needed to be able to come out the
other end and now help guys going
through the struggles with their heal
health so my key areas of interest in
men's health are complex troubleshooting
cases involving multiple hormonal
Pathways and or intractable conditions
as well as the psychological
implications of hormone disruption and
optimization or as I like to put it I
like to unfuck people so couple of
thoughts these are quotation marks I'm
quoting myself uh we have difficulty
integrating the intrinsic learned
experience of life being hard
particularly the burden of
responsibility of being adult males I
think one thing that's difficult when
you come of age whenever you deem that
to be is realizing that life is harder
as an adult than it was when you were a
kid and it's not all rainbows and
sunshine and it involves a lot of work
that we don't really want to do to get
the things we want and there's a lot of
[__] going on that we have to juggle and
we have to look after ourselves and
other people I think that's a big burden
and I
think understanding that and really
embodying and coming to terms with that
is a difficulty that a lot of guys go
through in their late 20s and early
30s we have difficulty with the burden
of self-awareness navigating guilt
impulses headism in the modern world as
well as the meaning of life purpose and
overall meaning what I mean by this is
that we have gotten to the point where
we have we've become so intelligent or
some of us we have become so sentient
that we can question the meaning of why
we're here we can even put the
well-being of the food chain before ours
veganism and we have gotten to the point
where intelligence and depression and
anxiety are correlated this is because
we can become self
torturing so I came up with this I think
this is a nice little uh summary of how
a lot of people are feeling when they
come to see me is there's nothing like
the self-awareness of watching yourself
[__] your own life up while
simultaneously not being able to
emotionally keep your [__] together
while you're doing it I get a lot of
guys in that situation so I went and saw
Jordan Peterson and vus uh a few weeks
ago before I came here and he made a
really good point about how we are very
attracted to the story of the hero in
narratives and he had this point and he
said we know the hero's journey so why
don't we walk the path of the hero so
why are we in this situation I think
there's these are just all my ideas and
what I've thought about this none of
this is uh objective fact but I think
life has gotten acutely easier but
chronically more stressful I think
things are more convenient and things
are more bubble wrapped and a lot of the
immediate stresses have gone but I think
now there's a whole bunch of unfamiliar
stress and noise that we haven't evolved
with and I think that life is equally
difficult overall it's just that that
challenge is more spaced out across
chronic stress and we know that humans
aren't that good at dealing with chronic
stress so life is also more noisy and
disconnected so communities have broken
down we spoke about the state of male
friendships already in this conference
we have a reduction in capacity and
resilience this is a really big one and
I think one thing that underpins this is
we no longer have or value the right of
passage so we've replaced the right of
passage with a sweet 16 that's replacing
something that's toughening for
something that is entitlement and
privilege that is a big net difference
so we are not valuing or encouraging men
to become strong and resilient and
capable and then we're seeing the
outcome of that when guys get into their
20s and 30s and they can't keep their
[__] together just looking after basic
stuff
the modern diet has made us frail and
reduced our capacity for power and
endurance we are Downstream of swapping
animal fat out for vegetable oil and we
are seeing the repercussions of reducing
the amount of meat in the diet and
increasing the amount of crap so modern
society has made us complacent fragile
and neurotic these are three personality
types that I find quite common people
who were avoidant people who were
snowflakes and people who become OCD
over useless [__] that saps their
attention and energy the modern
lifestyle rewards the wrong thing by
design it is rigged against you things
are made to distract you things are made
to make you feel inadequate so you'll
spend your money on [__] you don't need
it is by design that it's this way these
condition us away from capacity and
resilience and towards subservience so
we want people healthy enough that you
can pay your taxes but we don't want you
healthy enough that you can Thrive and
question what's going on it's a nice
little sweet spot seeking the path of
least resistance is baked into our
mamalian hindbrain so we are humans who
have evolved in times of scarcity
meaning that we will default towards the
easy path but the problem is when all
the paths have been made easy this can
lead to us becoming fragile or
anti-rent I don't think anti-rent is a
real word so self-awareness and critical
thinking are beaten out of us by the
education system we are taught to
regurgitate and do as we are told and
that's basically it Society is
engineered to distract weaken and sicken
the population I think most of us are
aware of this to some degree and a good
example of this hyper palatable
hypercaloric nutrient devoid processed
food AKA crap and softcore pornography
AKA Instagram are only a few button
presses away so few key points that I'm
going to be popping up this golden key
for today when we lack self-awareness
and when we're left to our own devices
without purpose accountability and
discipline hyperpower B highly processed
nutrient devoid junk food in every
street corner combined with booze and a
sedentary lifestyle will destroy our
health on a greater scale than
infectious disease motor vehicle
accidents sharks snakes and spiders
combined I like things in threes
so I'm going to be talking about this
concept today from the movie Cars um a
couple of things I don't know [__] about
cars so if my analogies are not
technically correct just pret pretend
they are you get the point but what I'd
like to talk about is this concept of
The Human Experience that we're all
having together is a series of
interconnected systems and our
Consciousness is connected to all these
systems so our Consciousness feeds into
all our organ systems and all our organ
systems feed into our Consciousness in
various ways this is not as esoteric and
woo woo as it sounds
so when medicine views organs muscular
and sceletal systems as large
independent rather than interdependent
we separate our Consciousness from our
biology so we look at physical health
and mental health as two separate things
and this is coin the term mental health
so Concepts like leaky gut the gut brain
axis neurosteroids like pregnant alone
DHEA carnivore and paleo diets theyve
all begun to explore this concept
further and psychedelic therapies and
breath work also explore these
connections so I would argue that many
not all many mental health conditions
can be underpinned and or triggered by
experiencing a diseased biological
experience of being alive so for example
if you have a man who does not develop
properly androgenic let's say that his
diet and lifestyle was terrible during
puberty his parents were unhealthy when
he was conceived and he gets to maybe
let's say 25 years old and he's never
had a day of optimal androgens in his
life we're going to get a guy who's got
a completely different trajectory for
where he's heading with his life a
completely different Baseline state of
his mental health because he didn't get
that androgenic surge to form his body
and his brain but also his identity so
he's gone through the world afraid he's
gone through the world lower energy he's
gone through the world intimidated by
other males and this gives him a
completely different experience for the
formative years of his life and it is no
wonder that these guys form things like
generalized anxiety disorder social
anxiety disorder or live a life that
leads to them becoming
depressed so this can form the
experiences you have the values and
attitudes by which you view yourself and
the world around you so it's important
that we look at how we view ourselves
versus how we view everything else and
sabotaging this Foundation can derail
the trajectory of one's life this is why
I'm so passionate about guys
understanding the importance of getting
comprehensive blood work done and
looking at the foundation of your health
so another key Point early onset disease
States botched or harmful medical
interventions this happens all the time
unnecessary surgeries inappropriate
medical prescriptions ssris as well as
acute stresses or injur or injuries
triggering autoimmune conditions can act
to saurs for the future dor everyone's
life so a chronically inflamed
metabolically compromised State during
puberty and early adulthood will lead to
drastically different physical and
mental outcomes and shifting this life
trajectory so what I want to look at
here is this concept that you are a
sentient and complex interconnected
machine experiencing itself being alive
this is the the lived experience that
we're having as humans and I think a
good example of this is Lightning
McQueen so that's you so this is a car
this is a mechanical system which is
also alive and I think that that's a
great way to look at the human body so
one thing that makes this complex when
we're looking at how this shows up in
the world is that you're now having this
experience with billions of other people
having this experience and then
interacting with the common environment
at the same time this leads to complex
[__] happening in life so many chronic
lowgrade mental health conditions
generalized anxiety disorder social
anxiety disorder bipolar bipolar type
two which is bipolar without the M the
manic episodes inattentive ADHD and
minor depressive disorder can often be
underpinned by consciously experiencing
the outcome of this mechanical problem
if you've had undiagnosed hypothyroidism
your whole life and you've gone through
the world in a low energy State your
body is going to have a much more uh
trigger happy stress response because
your body is used to kicking into the
adrenal system just to get things done
and you're also going to be more prone
to weight gain you're going to be more
exercise avoidant and you're going to be
generally down lethargic and it is no
wonder that this is so closely
correlated with depression because we're
actually experiencing ing a low energy
state in the body and the mind which by
definition is what depression is this
creates depressed bodies which create
depressed Minds because we're
experiencing that body being alive so
questions to ask yourself how good of a
driver can you be with a faulty vehicle
if you're a middle-aged gentleman in
your 40s and 50s let's say and you had
optimal testosterone levels up until you
know let's say 40 and then maybe you had
a testicular injury maybe you got
particular kicked in the nuts by someone
who was a jerk who knows but if you had
your formative life experience around
having an optimal vehicle and healthy
testosterone levels you're going to be
much better at keeping your [__]
together while you're running on fumes
you're going to have learned discipline
you're going to have learned the
resilience you're going to have formed
your identity around being a healthy
capable adult male I would hope however
if someone comes up like these younger
guys and they've never had optimal
testosterone a day in their lives
they're already geriatric testosterone
levels by the time
2122 how good of a driver can we
realistically expect them to be if their
first car is a piece of [__] if their
first car is constantly malfunctioning
then it's no wonder why they're getting
to 24 25 26 with no skills no resilience
no Organization no discipline unhealthy
bodies and unhealthy mental processes
because they're responding to the
environment they're reacting to their
internal biology and this makes a lot of
sense so how far will you fall short
driving a faulty vehicle over a decade
this is why people getting their blood
work done when they're young and working
out these problems are so important
because if you've got something like
hashimotos or intractable hypogonadism
at 20 and you leave it unchecked until
40 one you've lost your golden years but
two the trajectory of where you're going
to end up I mean are you going to be
able to be a capable provider are you
going to be able to be a capable father
I mean that's you're basically rigging
the game against you to lose and the
problem is when you go to the GP they're
not trained to look for these things or
check these things properly you have to
seek someone out who can actually look
at things preventatively and go hey are
you all good to go so next point if you
fix the vehicle right if you get your
car service so let's go back to the
example of the guy who's had the shitty
car from when he started if you fix the
vehicle will that instantly make you a
better driver this is what happens when
younger guys go on trt 24 2526 they
optimize their testosterone levels but
what if the vehicle was [__] because
they just trashed their bodies for the
formative years of their life what if
they had low testosterone for a reason
what if it was from binge drinking what
if it was from eating junk food not
going outside not doing any of the
things that you're supposed to be doing
and not doing all the things that you
are supposed to be doing I think that
this is something that is very common
and then the problem is we go oh you
trashed your old vehicle here's a brand
new sports car what do we expect going
to happen they're just going to crash it
they're going to get side effects
they're not going to get they're not
going to instantly become better drivers
because we haven't taught them the
skills that they were lacking which
damaged the vehicle in the first place
so great quote from Fat Bastard I eat
because I'm unhappy I'm unhappy because
I eat it's iconic so is the problem
biological or psychological one of my
favorite sayings with when working with
guys is you can't out biology your
psychology and you can't out psychology
your biology so a lot of the time you
have to make interventions on both sides
so is the biology an outcome of the bad
psychology showing up over time or is
theor psychology and outcome of the bad
biology I.E is it the chicken or the egg
did you adopt these negative
degenerative henis habits because life
was just so stressful and difficult
because you were sick or has life become
stressful and difficult and you are now
sick because of these destructive
hedonistic and degenerative choices that
people make so again I don't know [__]
about cars so maybe I'm being an
idealist but this is how I imagine
things look like if you go to a good
mechanic emphasis on that part
so you explain the details of your
issues they pop the bonnet look under
the hood work out what's going on go on
the skateboard go under the car check
that [__] as well and then they form a
hypothesis of the issue they go okay
this is probably what's going on and we
also found a whole bunch of extra [__]
that's going to cost you another $5,000
too and then ideally you regularly bring
your car back to the same mechanic so
the mechanic's familiar with your car is
what I assume people do and to keep on
top of it at an interval to keep the car
serviced so you go in for a checkup
every x amount of miles or every X
months as opposed to waiting until the
wheels fly off and then going back
because we know that if we do that the
bill is bigger so we can work it out
with our cars so what happens when you
take your body to a good health provider
okay and this is going to disqualify
most health providers so you explain the
details of the issue as well as review
your previous medical history so 50% of
providers are now gone they don't give
you enough time to do that so 50%
remaining the provider runs
comprehensive testing that's the rest of
them gone including diet and lifestyle
habits gone and performs a full analysis
of the person's capacity to perform and
operate holistically and uncovers any
issues humans are [__] complex and
you cannot work out the full breadth of
someone's problem in 15 minutes and
glancing over a few blood results it is
not possible so the provider then forms
a hypothesis of how the issues uncovered
could causing the symptoms described
this matches that and further explains
how the issues may have come about so
it's good to have a root cause
hypothesis how did this happen and how
to prevent the issue from occurring
again that's ideal as well as commenting
on other areas that can be improved or
work on which arose while performing the
initial diagnosis this is how Health
visits are meant to go they don't go
like
this and then ideally you would bring
yourself back to the same provider to
keep on top of your health as in
preventative health care rather than
waiting for you to get sick and then
expecting them to be able to solve it
like a magician so this gets more
complicated when you've got Ricky Bobby
inside your head so the more complex
thing about this analogy is this guy
which is your mind so if we go back to
the analogy of driving and I really like
to look at mental health like a skill so
driving is a skill that must be taught
and high performance driving is a skill
that must be taught and practice
regularly the skill of atten
the skill of being able to be present in
the current moment the skill of
practicing gratitude the skill of focus
discipline these are all things that
have to be practiced regularly to be
able to continue to embody some people
will naturally be more disciplined than
other people fantastic some people will
learn to tie their shoes quicker than
the next kid but we don't assume that
the kid at school who can't tie his
shoes yet is mentally [__] and has
brain damage we assume they just need a
bit more time to be taught how to tie
their shoes we don't assume that they
need to be medicated or there's
something wrong with them mental health
needs to be viewed similarly so mental
health Focus Stress Management
intelligence impulse control delayment
of gratification these are all skills
and you have to learn them and practice
them otherwise you won't have them you
can't expect to have the results of
people who've done the work that you
didn't do that is called
entitlement so the prefrontal cortex
this is what separates us from our other
mamalian uh also creatures in this world
and what the prefrontal cortex does is
it controls executive function so a lot
of people who aren't doing well in life
lack executive functions this is things
like impulse control Focus emotional
regulation not flipping your lid and
reacting to things which are not well
thought through and emotional this is
how people [__] things up so knowing the
fix is easy but doing the work day after
day is the part where people fail
compliance is a science if I tell 10
guys to meditate 9 .9 of them are not
going to do it 0.1 of them will and it
will change his life but it's difficult
to get people to do the things that they
need to do especially when they suck at
them so if you need to do mobility and
stretch the stiffer you are and the more
uncomfortable it is to do Mobility that
means you need to do it it's not a
signal that oh no this isn't for you if
you walk into the gym and the five pound
dumbbell is so heavy you can't pick it
up you're not going to go oh that means
I don't need weights it means you do
need weights that's the point so if
you're sitting down and you can't be
with your mind at the end of the day if
you can't touch your toes if you wake up
stiff and sore you're getting these
signals from your body to actually do
the work that you've probably known that
you've needed to do for ages and
understand that you're not getting away
from it so we have talked about this
concept of meeting the medicine halfway
and I think this is a really good uh
topic to speak on which has been spoken
on so much here which is the idea that
you need to do the work for your
treatment to actually work for you so
Paul or reactive decisions often to self
soothe anxiety or solve a short-term
problem at the expense of one's future
self over time cause many preventable
and reversible chronic diseases such as
getting home at work from the end of the
day and instead of going to the gym
sitting on the couch and pouring a
double glass of whiskey doing that
consistently over time yes that may make
you feel better in the moment but what
you're doing one poisoning the body and
two the opportunity cost of missing
doing thing that's good for you is going
to add up and it's preventable and it's
also reversible so your Consciousness
can be your greatest Ally or enemy can
keep you on track through insurmountable
adversity or it can betray you leading
you to self-destructive degenerative
vies so your conscious experience is the
lens you live and perceive the world
around you through so you want to curate
the experience that you're having so
that you can see the world through
better goggles this will impact your
experience of being alive things like
practicing gratitude things like having
better cardiovascular fitness all of
these things are very important for how
you feel and how you show up every day
not to mention the importance of putting
good quality food into your body being a
lean healthy body fat percentage and not
poisoning your body with things that
don't need to be in that so your
Consciousness is a product of your
experiences and this is why hormone
replacement therapy is so important that
we give it time guys need time to get
their life on a winning streak to feel
good about themselves that's how you fix
depression and anxiety as Jordan
Peterson says competence creates
confidence it takes a while to get good
at [__] so that you can be proud of the
things that you do so this is something
that takes time and it's important that
we focus on experiential therapy a lot
of the time talk therapy doesn't work
for these guys they don't need to sit
and talk and understand that they're a
piece of [__] they might already know
that that's going to make it worse so
what we need to do is create experiences
that guys are proud of for overcoming
learning martial arts is one of the most
empowering things guys can do absolutely
working on things like uh low intensity
steady state cardio that can be one of
the most profoundly meditative
experiences that you have because you're
constantly wanting to [__] out of it
but you continue to put one foot in
front of the other this is the skill of
discipline so these are experiences that
we have to practice regularly to be able
to build the capacity and build the
things that we're proud of so that we
can go through life actually proud of
ourselves so your mind gets feedback
from your internal biology and external
environment and creates meaning through
your experiences values attitudes and
programming this is life so the stories
you tell about yourself and who you are
and how you relate to the world are
subject to plasticity so this is what we
spoke about with silvery and micro doing
yesterday is that The Narrative of who
you are in the life that you're living
this is something that you can rewrite
in real time this is something that you
can change if you're the person that
hits snooze every morning you can just
stop being that person who hits snooze
tomorrow if you want to
just don't hit the button you can these
things are subject to change and you as
the the person in charge you as the
driver you do have that power to go in
and break your shitty destructive habits
you just need to be able to have the
skill and the determination to be able
to do that and these are things that
require practice so you have the power
to hijack your experience of reality if
you have the power to exert your will
I've met people who say there's no such
thing as free will and they were all
people who were not happy with where
they were in their life I truly believe
that a lot of people do not have the
capacity to exert their free will but it
doesn't mean that it's not something
that you can do if you work on it and
this is something that you work on
through doing difficult things that push
you outside your comfort zone like
training
fasting uh different forms of martial
arts learning different physical
disciplines and then also in the moment
learning to focus your mind to regulate
your thoughts and attention through
things like mindfulness meditation so
I'm going to go I'm going to bring it
back to some Neuroscience before we wrap
up so that we can call it a science talk
so dopamine transmission is a key to our
lived experience all the biohackers love
the dopamines right we all want more
dopamine dopamine is the best when it
comes to dopamine though it's important
that you earn it you don't just piss out
dopamine for no reason unless you're
taking amphetamines I mean you can stare
at a wall and take amphetamines and your
brain will light up like a Christmas
tree but when we're looking at how
damine Pathways work in real life it's
not about flooding your brain with
dopamine for free it's about getting the
optimal amount of dopamine in response
to doing the thing that you're supposed
to be doing and what we have to do is
train ourselves to become addicted and
Reliant to getting the dopamine from
things that are good for you not things
that are bad for you because gambling
alcohol and video games will increase
dopamine just like exercise will so we
have to condition ourselves to be able
to be addicted to the right things to be
able to have that quality experience of
life and feel good but not destroy our
health in the process so the higher
capacity for dopamine production and
synthesis means good things feel better
but it does not give you that reward for
free so when you optimize things like
testosterone thyroid DHEA and even
pregnanolone to some degree what we're
doing is we're increasing the capacity
for dopamine transmission meaning that
your brain will make more dopamine in
responses to the things that feel good
and it will also allow your brain to
handle higher of dopamine over time when
it gets used to this so this is
extremely important because this means
that we are now going to feel better
from the things that are supposed to
feel good which can resolve and
eliminate anhedonic behavioral patterns
when things that are supposed to feel
good don't really hit the sides we're
not going to go out and actually do
these things these hobbies and these
social interactions because we're just
not getting that signal we'd rather just
stay at home lay on the couch and be in
a low energy State because we're
overwhelmed with stress by just is doing
basic [__] because the vehicle that
we're driving is sick and needs a
service so androgens also have a complex
interaction with Biology and neurology
so what happens in your body and what
happens in your brain so many of the
positive outcomes of TR stem from
testosterone's influence on the brain
psychology and Consciousness even in
training a lot of the androgenic benefit
comes from increasing your power output
through your central nervous system so
testosterone does a bunch of cool [__]
in the brain it balances out a lot of
the effects of cortisol and stress this
is very important because when you can
modulate the stress pathway all of a
sudden you're going to be able to want
to overcome the stresses in life because
yes they'll feel stressful and difficult
but the feeling of conquering and
overcoming something bigger than
yourself feels even better when you've
got low testosterone you're just getting
a [__] ton of the stress and none of the
good stuff so you're going to avoid all
the hardship to keep yourself safe and
this is what happens when younger men
are low in testosterone during their
formative years they're not like yeah I
want to go take on the world I want to
be an entrepreneur I want to start my
business I want to do all these
challenging things and take a swing at
life and see what I can do they don't do
that what they want to do is they want
to stay at home they want to get paid
the most amount of money to do the least
amount of work so that life can be as
comfortable and cushy as possible and
then you can play video games jerk off
and get the easy dopamine pathway
because your body can't handle the
stress it needs to show up and get the
things done that you need to do just to
even tread water we also balance the
guard G and glutamate transmission so
DHT is particularly important for
balancing Garber transmission so we're
looking at Garber and glutamate it's
like the brakes in the accelerator on
neuronal uh excitedness we'll call it so
when you have increased glutamate to
Gaba your excitatory neurotransmission
is over stimulated and what this can
feel like is a racing monkey mind this
constant low grade state of my brain's
always running around and I can't focus
on anything and I can't switch my mind
off and it's this horrible Perpetual
wired and Tide feeling that's when your
glutamate and Garba Transmissions out of
whack so what all of these things also
do particularly DHT is increasing
norepinephrine and Garber signaling as
well so norepinephrine is like your
brain's version of adrenaline and Garber
is like your brain's version of Valium
so when you combine those things
together what you're getting kind of
like a yab bomb is you're getting a
driven focused and calm State this is
what creates the energy and the capacity
of a leader this is very important so
this has the capacity to manifest and
key to this point it doesn't give you it
for free it has the capacity to manifest
as courage bravery and resilience if you
apply yourself this Foundation is the
opposite to generalized and social
anxiety disorder and creates the
opportunity to overcome learned fear I
don't like the term generalized anxiety
I don't like the term social anxiety I
find that these people are not anxious
they're afraid and I think learned fear
is a good example because they're
fearful of the environment because they
went through it at the bottom of the
food chain they went through it as a
prey animal not as a predator it makes
sense that you're programmed to be
afraid I'd be afraid if I was prey so
breaking the cycle of learned fear
paralysis by analysis I like that term
because it Rhymes procrastination and
the resulting guilt and low self-esteem
is vital for men to get their health and
life trajectory on track
as I said there's nothing like [__]
up your own life and not being able to
handle watching yourself do it
so this is a key Point here a lot of
young men lack the skill of not being
able to do work that they don't want to
do say I can only focus on things I
really enjoy [__] dude like good
luck that's a skill and that's a skill
that is not an easy skill to learn but
it's a skill that we can all learn if we
have the right motivators so the short
term and long-term consequences of not
being able to do the work that you need
to do that you don't want to do one it
will completely Hydra the trajectory of
your life but then it also gets
diagnosed as mental health disorders and
medicated with psychos stimulants and
anti-depressants so chronic inflammation
this is a buzz word uh this disrupts
dopamine production and synthesis while
increasing reuptake so this is terms
that get argued about and confused about
online if you're in chronic pain or you
have something physically wrong with
your body like you're obese your body
will objectively be more inflamed
systemically that is how it works so
when you have increased levels of
systemic inflammation this will reduce
the amount of dopamine that you make it
will reduce the amount of dopamine that
gets into the receptor and it will
increase how fast it up took out it's
like three negatives for wanting to
increase dopamine so if you want to feel
better understand that chronic
inflammation is like anti-cocaine it's
not what you want so
this is something that we want to fix is
understand that phys fixing the physical
body particularly when you're in a
chronic disease state is fundamental to
the foundation of your mental health so
chronic inflammation increases neural
oxidative stress so it sets your mind on
fire which can be subjectively
experienced as an anxious racing mind
things feel [__] and you can't switch
your mind off horrible so experiencing
being a physically unhealthy body being
alive going through day-to-day life
feels more stressful than it should so
we know that chronic inflammatory states
are associated with poor mental health
outcomes while positive diet and
exercise interventions improve mental
health we know this this is very well
documented so as uh Dr Hotchkis
referenced in my in his talk yesterday
uh I think a good point to start with
and the whole war and masculinity part
two which is a part of this uh
recordings you can access goes
specifically into breaking down what you
should and shouldn't do lays it all out
very clearly but I would summarize it as
do the things your grandma told told you
to do go outside more get more Sunshine
eat your meat and veg don't play too
many video games I think those things
are very good pieces of advice which are
Fallen a bit out of favor so going back
to this entitlement mentality you cannot
expect to feel mentally healthy typo
while being physically unhealthy doesn't
make any sense the only way that you can
do that is if you take SSRI
anti-depressants to trick your brain
into think you're doing better than you
are that's how they work so if you want
to feel your best mentally you can work
towards this by becoming your best
physically so your body must be primed
to and scheduled to release endorphins
this means you need to be able to move
with good cardiovascular fitness so that
you can move your body in a way that
gives you that run as high chronically
inflamed States disrupt natural opioid
and endorphin function so it's the
opposite of that so these things will
make you feel fantastic if you move and
feel alive but if your body is in pain
and inflamed your Baseline state is
going to be much more miserable you must
be able to and regularly perform cardio
in inputs to trigger the endoc canabo
runners High your car was made to drive
you are the apex predator of Mother
Nature your body was made to move and
driving it feels good when you have a
good car and you know how to drive it so
you are constantly experiencing a
biological reaction to your most recent
meals you are constantly experiencing a
biological reaction to the sum of your
habits and your lifestyle choices you
are what you eat and you are what you do
so these are things that you can change
tomorrow if you want to but you need to
change them consistently over time a lot
of people need to change their diet and
lifestyle and then they need to be the
guy who changed their lifestyle years
ago and they need to be the product of
doing that consistently yes you'll feel
better when you change it acutely but to
feel the best you possibly can you just
need to do it consistently over time so
you are in real time experiencing a
psychological reaction to the present
moment which is where we're at we are
now Ju toose with your memories of the
past and anticipation for what the
future holds and that's why it's so
important that we rewrite our own
stories to be grateful and to be proud
of ourselves so that we don't go into
the future afraid of the unknown but
feeling confident that we can actually
take on what's on the other side we are
often blindly steering the ship of our
life into an iceberg in the present
moment while your mind thinks about what
already happened yesterday and what
might happen tomorrow meanwhile you are
steering straight into the [__]
Iceberg so put the best things in into
your body if you want to feel your best
Common Sense put good fuel in the car if
you want it to drive better if you put
the worst things your in your body like
drugs alcohol and junk food you need to
have the expectation that that's going
to make you feel like [__] so if you
want to have optimal outputs it's
fundamentally dependent on the quality
of the inputs as the foundation so focus
on the kilograms of food you eat every
week not the grams of supplements or the
milligrams of
medications your car was not made to be
driven for 30 minutes a day or 4 hours a
week while you sit in your computer
chair or lay in bed for the rest of it
it is not how we invol evolved you are
the dominant bloodline of Mother
Nature's apex predator so we're at the
top of the food chain and then all of
our ancestors they all got killed off by
various plagues Wars scarcities nature
we survived so our bloodline is the
dominant bloodline and we're at the top
of the food chain and that's how we're
able to have this conversation today and
people are struggling to make the and go
outside so there is so much capacity in
our DNA for greatness and there is so
much capacity to excel we just have to
understand that we need to change the
inputs change the outputs over time to
be able to embody that without sounding
too entitled that Birthright of actually
feeling and being capable so it takes
conscious daily and intentional work to
undo the majority of spending your
waking hours sitting it takes a lot of
work and time dedicate time for daily
movement across a variety of movement
patterns so if you've been sitting
non-stop for years you might need to do
more than 10 or 15 minutes of Mobility a
day to make progress if you haven't
stretched or done mobility in years you
have years of this to catch up on so you
need to look at doing more work so much
of the work I see people do is
maintenance load if you're trying to
correct something correct a deficit you
need to work harder and do more volume
so work on power endurance flexibility
strength hypertrophy and stability you
got to do all of it yoga meditation and
iio as I said before these feel terrible
when you need them the most but when you
get good at them they actually become
addictive so get addictive to the stuff
that makes your body sing so it feels
and sorry to anyone who has a Suzuki
Swift if you feel better it sorry it
feels better to drive through life as a
sports car or a performance SUV that'll
run down Suzuki Swift so if you want to
change your experience for the years
that we have left in this world start by
upgrading your car understand that the
Final Destination so if you're looking
for like what my purpose in the world
why am I here what's the meaning of all
of this and if you don't know that's
okay your purpose at the moment is
working out what that is so it still
means that you can move forward the
Final Destination may not be clear from
where you're at now but you still know
how to progress forward and for all you
know that end destination will become
clear once you're further down the line
so focus on being better tomorrow than
you are today and don't be this guy I
haven't seen actually this part of the
movie but he doesn't look too happy so
don't be him don't be a hypochondriac
don't worry about every tiny little
minuscule thing that's wrong with your
body and let it sap all your attention
and energy and take away your focus of
enjoying the world don't obsess over
every little noise you hear your car
make every little macro that's out of
whack every little thing that's not
optimal in your protocol let that go
okay that's neurotic let it go so that
you can have a good experience dayto day
don't be that guy the further you are
off track the greater story it will be
when you get back on track and you know
Alex puts it that you have nothing to
lose I think that's a good way to look
at it I think if you're down and out and
I think if you know if you're at if
you're at the bottom if you're if you're
right at Rock
Bottom I think you have the opportunity
to swing back at life so hard that it
shocks other people and I think that
viewing things in this way viewing
things is an opportunity finding ways to
brainwash yourself with narratives that
serve you is what's going to allow you
to get out of those dark places and move
ahead so I've got five steps and if you
watch the other talks you'll know these
but I'm going to go through them again
because you have to sit here and listen
to me for another few minutes so I think
these are really important and I think
that everyone can go through this
regardless of where you're at so number
one reverse engineer becoming the best
version of yourself and what do I mean
by that I don't mean by I want to become
exactly like that guy exactly like this
guy you want to adopt traits of people
who Inspire or Mentor you and put your
own spin on them and think what would
the best version of me do how would he
look what would his daily habit be what
would he eat how would he treat other
people and you want to start embodying
those practices and principles and look
at a way that you can get yourself from
where you are now to where that guy is
in the smallest increments possible so
that you have somewhere to start
from understand and accept that you must
play the ball where it lands some people
get dealt a really shitty hand some
people get dealt a way worse hand than
other people some people get dealt great
hands and then get dealt their first
shitty hand and they can't handle it but
regardless of what hand you've been
dealt you still have to play it so
accepting that ball has to be played
where it lands is often the first step
so take radical positive action to make
your trt work for you don't sit back and
expect your trt to work on you and turn
you into gigachad it's not going to do
that on its own I've seen a lot of guys
take a lot of testosterone and not do a
lot of work and the results are all the
same so testosterone will be a
multiplier for all the positive diet and
lifestyle practices that you employ over
time understand that puberty takes years
so optimizing your testosterone and
being the end result of optimized
testosterone takes years so measure
progress in how far you've come not how
far you are from your goal otherwise you
can be demoralized even though you've
made significant progress so always be
looking at how far you've come not how
far you have left to go and finally I
think this one's really important is
give yourself a reason to be proud of
yourself I think it's so important that
we go through life proud of ourselves
otherwise it just leads to anxiety and
depression but I also think that life
doesn't come with participation medals
and your brain knows that partic
participation medals are [__] anyway
they don't work they don't mean anything
so you actually have to go out there and
earn a reason to be proud of yourself
and I have found that men who are proud
of themselves that is one of the best
things to cure insomnia when you're
laying there awake at night and your
mind is racing when you get to the
bottom of why it's keeping you awake a
lot of the time it's guilt a lot of the
time it's wasted potential a lot of the
time it's not showing up up the way that
you wanted to show up so be proud of the
person that you are be proud of the
world being a better place because
you're in it and be proud of leaving the
world a better place than you found it
and I think that if you fixate on those
kind of values you'll be much happier
and better off for it so that's all
thank
[Applause]
you